<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks upon Remarques, or, A vindication of the conversations of the town in another letter directed to the same Sir T.L.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12818192</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12818192</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58507)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks upon Remarques, or, A vindication of the conversations of the town in another letter directed to the same Sir T.L.</title>
                  <author>T. L., Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.C. for William Hensman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An answer to "Remarques on the humours and conversations of the town, written in a letter to Sir T.L." 1673.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Remarques on the humours and conversations of the town.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Social life and customs --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Remarks upon Remarques:</hi> OR, A VINDICATION OF THE CONVERSATIONS OF THE TOWN, In another LETTER directed to the ſame Sir <hi>T. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quare fremuerunt Gentes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.C.</hi> for <hi>William Henſman,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Head</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_lady_madam">
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt vertuos Lady Madam <hi>R. C.</hi> Who requeſted this <hi>Vindication.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Need not <hi>vindicate</hi> the <hi>Town</hi> to <hi>you:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You,</hi> being <hi>here,</hi> that Office bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do.</l>
               <l>The Vertues <hi>you</hi> poſſeſs, and <hi>All</hi> Adore,</l>
               <l>Expiate for the <hi>Vice</hi> of <hi>Town,</hi> and more.</l>
               <l>I'd ſet <hi>your</hi> Picture on my Book, but then,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It</hi> would fore ſtall the Market of my <hi>Pen:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:94173:3"/>
               <l>And <hi>none</hi> would read; or ſome (perhaps) would <hi>ſwear</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Town</hi> needs no <hi>vindication,</hi> while ſhe's there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſince <hi>ſome</hi> know you not, and <hi>ſome</hi> forget;</l>
               <l>Ile let <hi>them</hi> know, I've done the <hi>Task</hi> you ſet.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_gentlemen">
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:3"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Well-bred</hi> GENTLEMEN of the <hi>TOWN.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Lately met with a Linſey-woolſey Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as like what the Common-Lawyers call a <hi>Libel</hi> as ever it could look; I read it over, and found a diſcontented <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body,</hi> (who ſeems to know
<pb facs="tcp:94173:4"/>nothing of the Town, but what is not worth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) labouring to <hi>Traveſt London</hi> into extream de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities, by laying the blemiſhes of <hi>ſome</hi> rude Acquaintance of <hi>his,</hi> upon the <hi>whole</hi> Town: like the <hi>Country-man,</hi> who having found <hi>ſome</hi> Tares in his Diſh, ſwore there was no Wheat in his Frumity. Then to ſhew himſelf a <hi>VVriter,</hi> to humour ſome preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced Party, or for ſome other ends, with open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,
<pb facs="tcp:94173:4"/>proclaims to the World, that our <hi>Age,</hi> our <hi>Nation,</hi> and its great <hi>Metropolis,</hi> are <hi>wholly</hi> (for his Notions are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral) degenerate, vitious, and debauched</p>
            <p>I thought it a <hi>bold</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, and pregnant with dangerous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences: As firſt, It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages and diſſwades all Country Gentlemen from educating their Sons in the ways of <hi>Arts, Arms,</hi> and <hi>Trade.</hi> It prophanes the moſt <hi>Learned</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:94173:5"/>Glorious City in the Chriſtian World. And (which is worſt of all, by defaming <hi>that</hi>) it impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the Government <hi>thereof,</hi> and offers vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the Conduct of <hi>our Governours,</hi> who have always thought fit to make this renowned City the Center of diſtributive Juſtice, and the ſeat of the <hi>Imperial</hi> Diadem.</p>
            <p>On this laſt ſcore, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, it ſeemed to my ſenſe, to ſmell <hi>hot</hi> of a Deſign, againſt which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb facs="tcp:94173:5"/>had a juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that is, by oblique means to poſſeſs the heads of the Ignorant, unſtable Populace, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>perſonal</hi> defects of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, ſuch Arts have been Comets portending future Evils, fore-runners of Rebellion.</p>
            <p>It was well ſaid by the Lord <hi>Digby</hi> in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in 1640. <hi>It is eaſie to make People believe, what they are willing to believe, though the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:94173:6"/>are little inducing, that are uſed to engage that belief.</hi> As when the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition in that Year was drawn up, and preſented to the Commons againſt Biſhops, the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences therein ſuppoſed, were moſt perſonal, the other ridiculous: As be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Ovids De Arte A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandi,</hi> was Tranſlated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Engliſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, (though I was <hi>moved</hi> to what I have done by Arguments of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Nature, yet) theſe
<pb facs="tcp:94173:6"/>conſiderations prompted me to comply with the other deſires; And ſince I have done this, I ſend it to <hi>you</hi> (as an Eſſay only) who (being equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned with <hi>me</hi> in the Cauſe) will, I hope, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply (on occaſion) what is omitted, and correct what is amiſs, which will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gentlemen <hi>Your affectionate Friend and Townſman.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:7"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Intend no reflections on any Country Gentlemen, but thoſe of meer Country built, void of Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>I intend no vindication, but of the Sober and Vertuous in the <hi>Town.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94173:8"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Lately ſaw a Letter, ſaid to be written to you, grown into a Book, and called <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marques on the Humours and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations of the Town.</hi> I liked the Name, and expected much from it: But when I found that its buſineſs was to perſwade you to a meer Country life, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you wholy from <hi>London,</hi> I wondred what a Gods name was in the mans mind: and when further I ſaw his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments perſwaſive to be only ſome minute Conſiderations of Country Paſtimes, and Fools-Bables, and the diſwaſive Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94173:9"/>
               <hi>ſome</hi> rudeneſſes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies in <hi>London,</hi> I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred more; eſpecially, while he wiſhes you to <hi>Arrive at the glory of your Anceſtors, to ſtick freſh Lawrels in their Garlands, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Hero;</hi> and diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wades you from the Regular Method of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing the deſign.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſince he took upon him to be a Tutor to you, and adviſe you to become a <hi>Hero,</hi> he ſhould have let you know the <hi>ways</hi> to be ſuch; to have read you Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures thereupon, to have inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated the advantages of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Courſes, the inconveniences of the ills, which his <hi>long Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> has prompted him to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marque</hi> upon; to have informed you that in (the Univerſity of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94173:9"/>
               <hi>London,</hi> there are of both ſorts, of the better ſort, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part; and againſt the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer to have framed his Cautions to avoid intimacy, converſe, and indeed acquaintance with them. But in ſtead thereof he point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blank tells you, you muſt not go to <hi>London.</hi> And why ſo? Truly, Sir, he uſes you like a child, and would ſcare you from <hi>London</hi> with the Buggers of the Country; and by Country Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, there are naughty People in <hi>London,</hi> therefore you muſt not come there. There is in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Bridewel, Newgate, Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem; <hi>Ergo</hi> all the People in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> are Whores, Thieves, or Mad.</p>
            <p>Sir, Since the man was fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94173:10"/>with anger enough, and ſome words, why did he not take his riſe at the Univerſities, to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue you into a <hi>Hero?</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancing in <hi>Cambridge</hi> for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he might have held forth, and ſaid, O dear, Sir, Remember the Glories that attend the Ghoſts of your renowned Anceſtors, the Excellencies of an Indulgent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, exceeding the Preſidents of any Age, who deſires you ſhould arrive at heroick atchievements, to ſerve your King and Country, and become a <hi>Hero.</hi> Do not go to <hi>Cambridgé,</hi> Sir, there are <hi>Alehouſes,</hi> in which you <hi>will</hi> be drunk; and there are in thoſe houſes notable prinking Wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that <hi>will</hi> captivate you into Marriage, or ſomewhat like it.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94173:10"/>There are <hi>Tennis-Courts,</hi> and <hi>Bowling-Greens</hi> that <hi>will</hi> heat you to an exceſs, and then you <hi>will</hi> drink cold ſmall Beer and die. There is a River too, in which you <hi>will</hi> be drowned; and you <hi>will</hi> ſtudy your ſelf into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, or break your <hi>Brain;</hi> and <hi>will</hi> you go to ſuch a place? Next, Sir, for <hi>London;</hi> do not go thither, and then tell the Book, &amp;c. And as for Travel, Sir, never think on't; for there is a great Sea to go over, there is in it a great beaſtly Fiſh called a Whale, which (they ſay) turn over Ships, and drown the Folks therein; there are alſo Rocks, and Shelves, and Sands, which <hi>will</hi> Shipwrack you; and remember, Sir, a great <hi>Hurricane</hi> got away the Lord
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94173:11"/>
               <hi>Willoughby.</hi> And laſtly, as to this point, there are ſtrange People beyond Seas, not only the hateful <hi>French,</hi> whom we <hi>over-ape,</hi> but <hi>Black</hi> People, who look like De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and <hi>will</hi> fright you out of <hi>your Wits;</hi> and <hi>Wild</hi> People too, who <hi>will</hi> tear you in pieces limb from limb; and another ſort of People called <hi>Cannibals,</hi> who will eat up all thoſe limbs and pieces, even to the little Toe-nail, or the Griſtle of your Rump. What think you, Sir, of all this, will you now take ſuch courſes as theſe? No, I hope not, Sir, keep in the Country, and uſe the <hi>manly Exerciſe of Riding after a Deer,</hi> and I'le warrant you a <hi>Hero</hi> to ſome tune: but be ſure come not at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>there</hi> are ill People.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94173:11"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euge,</hi> brave Country Tutor! he has gueſſed at the Dimenſions of <hi>Hercules</hi> by his foot: but who taught him, by that foot, to know what manner of men were <hi>Agamemnon</hi> and <hi>Achilles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Finding the Adviſers Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to run after this manner, I began to gueſs where he had been bred; I judged he was a <hi>Funam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulo</hi> bred in the <hi>Town,</hi> for I thought by his high jingo's, and mighty curvetts on <hi>high-lines,</hi> he muſt have been acquainted with <hi>Jacob Hall,</hi> and <hi>Bartholomew Fair;</hi> and I perceive it was <hi>his</hi> ill luck to keep very bad Company, and that a great while too, by the knowledge he diſcovers in the Vices of his Companions. I profeſs, Sir, I have known that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94173:12"/>
               <hi>woful Town</hi> many years, and know very little of the Vices, but can give great Inſtances of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Learning and Converſation of the place; and though your Adviſer, Sir, has told me ſo much news, I am not frighted from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducating a Son in <hi>London,</hi> rather than to leave my Eſtate to an ill hew'n Logger-head, fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to run after a Dog and a Cat; and muſt be kept a Fool to become a Country <hi>Hero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I miſlike all undertakings that anatomize Vice in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Youth, and by that means tell them of the Vices whereof they never heard, and the way to be Vicious which they never knew. <hi>Nitimur in vetitum,</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come natural, ſince Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94173:12"/>depraved, and reſtrictions or prohibitions ought to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed warily. The old Man (in <hi>Arioſto</hi> the <hi>Italian</hi> Poet) who had not gone out of the Town for 40 years, hearing that he was confined to the Town, was mad to ſee what was without the Gates.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, It has pleaſed your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſer, that mighty perſon of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,</hi> next to your Mother, to go another way to work, and a ſure one too; infallible I promiſe you: an approved remedy againſt the <hi>Vices of London;</hi> and that is, in ſhort, never to come there. And all this upon good Reaſon and ſound, even the <hi>Calviniſtical Hypotheſis,</hi> that the <hi>Energetical Decrees</hi> of <hi>Reprobation, will</hi> catch
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94173:13"/>you by the back, as ſoon as you ſet foot in <hi>London</hi> ſtreets, <hi>O wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> London <hi>ſtreets!</hi> And <hi>long experience</hi> has taught him, that the fate attending the Life of a young Gentleman in <hi>London,</hi> is to be <hi>vicious, fottiſh, and prophane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I condole with him his <hi>ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> and am glad he has changed his Company, and has learned to be a <hi>Hero-maker,</hi> though ſuch a one as 'tis; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs 'tis better to be a Fool than a Knave, if there be a <hi>neceſsity</hi> of being one of them: but he has not uſed Arguments cogent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to convince me of the <hi>neceſsity</hi> of being one or the other. Sure this man, when he was a Raw Country Lad, was ſent to <hi>London,</hi> and there fell to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94173:13"/>
               <hi>Boyiſh</hi> art of making <hi>Squibs</hi> and <hi>Crackers,</hi> and ſo from one chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh trick to another, till he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved to the idle and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent courſes he now ſwaggers at. And Truth is, if young in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Country Gentlemen be not well taught, and well-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before they come there, if they be not grown men too, and perhaps be well appointed to theſe Deſignments and Societies, they may be impoſed upon, even by the very Boys of this place; who by the help of the frequent and generous converſe here, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to knowledge to 10 years of Age, in greater meaſure than a Country Bumpkin at 20.</p>
            <p>Perhaps, Sir, this man of <hi>Idaea's</hi> had ſome aſpiring thoughts to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94173:14"/>
               <hi>Bell-weather</hi> of the Wits, as he calls ſome <hi>Ainy, brisk</hi> Fellows of his acquaintance, to out-go the <hi>Coffee-houſe</hi> ſmoak, to reach the Clouds, to be Speaker of all the Noiſe that haunt idle places, and becauſe he could not reach the top of his aim, has taken it in dudgeon: or having felt the pains and aches, which (they ſay) ſucceed a diſſolute Youth, cries out, <hi>No London, no London;</hi> and may be himſelf, for ought I know, is like an old Ape (as one ſays, that has worn off his Tail, and would have all young Apes cut off their Tails to be like him. And but for one, <hi>perhaps</hi> more, perhaps he belonged to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, afraid of being pumped for not paying <hi>Exceedings,</hi> frighted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94173:14"/>at the Rebellion for that cauſe; for he ſays he was <hi>ſurpriſed,</hi> and his Letter was <hi>voided</hi> about that time; or by miſs of expected advantages he grew into wrath and fell foul of all <hi>London,</hi> only was pleaſed to be a little kinder to ſome of both Sexes, at the end of his Preface; but they are not very conſiderable neither, they are retired Animals, live to themſelves and their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and are no companions for you, Sir. So in effect he concludes, that <hi>all</hi> who will converſe are bad; and <hi>all</hi> are bad who will not converſe.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir, we are fallen into the way of the Wilderneſs, and if you pleaſe to tire your ſelf a little, I'le go along with you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94173:15"/>through the Wood, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are adviſed to Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) to encourage your ſteps, I'le tell you now and then a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as ſhall be occaſioned by the <hi>Remarques</hi> in our Travel. And now, for my Pebble and Sling, and have at the <hi>Philiſtim</hi> in Green, this Country <hi>Zanzumim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sir, before we go further I muſt take notice whom I walk with, what Company I keep; and 'tis a good rule for you, Sir, either in Town or Country, <hi>noſcitur ex ſocio, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Upon this firſt view of you, I take you to be a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of good Family, though the Gallantry of your Mother is the only Argument to make out the Quality of your Anceſtors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94173:15"/>the ſureſt ſide, was thought the ſureſt demonſtration alſo that you are dignified with the higheſt Order of Gentility, of good Eſtate, and having a <hi>round ſum of ready money;</hi> that you are come to the <hi>Age of Conſideration,</hi> that your Education has <hi>been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the ancient Precepts of Nobleneſs, Generoſity, and Vertue.</hi> So that you have paſſed all the <hi>Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucks</hi> of School and Univerſity ſafe and ſound, and whether you are to go to <hi>London</hi> with ſafety is the Queſtion. In order to that you have a Letter ſent, which begins with <hi>Trouble and Surprize;</hi> and I verily believe the good man wrote it quite through in that condition. But why <hi>Trouble,</hi> and why <hi>Surprize?</hi> Oh, a young
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94173:16"/>Gentleman, a young innocent Gentleman, who by an innocent, ignorant Country life, who by <hi>riding after a Deer</hi> might become a <hi>Hero,</hi> and eſpecially by living under the <hi>Regiment</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of an induigent <hi>Mother</hi> might be ſo; is now going to <hi>London,</hi> vile <hi>London!</hi> where are nothing but Mouſe-traps, and Fire-works, Bears and Lions, Skip-Jacks and Jews-trumps, and nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributary to the making of a <hi>Hero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſad and doleful poſture he laments the ſtate of this <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age,</hi> in compariſon with former <hi>Ages,</hi> and cries out with the Poet,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94173:16"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Aetas parentum pejor avis, tulit</l>
                  <l>Nos nequiores, mox daturos</l>
                  <l>Progeniem vitioſiorem. <hi>Hor.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And every Age may ſay the ſame, and perhaps truly, yet while the Vices of Ages are not recorded, and ſo are unknown to after-times, and preſent Ages have perſonal view of themſelves, they judge the preſent always worſt; and out of well wiſhes for amendment, it has been wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſigned to commend the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and rebuke the preſent Age: and the ſame <hi>aetas parentum, &amp;c.</hi> will be perhaps uſed by our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, though we have ſeen the horrid'ſt Times that have been ſince our Saviours.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94173:17"/>
            <p>It is true, the preſent time in which we now live, doth differ from the Times on this ſide <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and yet can compare with all before. The reaſon of the difference may in ſome ſort be, that after the Crown of <hi>England</hi> juſtified it ſelf <hi>Imperial,</hi> and the affair of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>Independent</hi> of either the Eaſtern or Weſtern Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs; our Iſlands dividing from all claims of Foreign Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and differing in ſome points of Religion, became eſtranged from Confederacies with other Nations, and ſo had not the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of training up our Youth in Martial Activities (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating what little <hi>formal</hi> Artillery was in the <hi>Netherlands</hi>) which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94173:17"/>brought our Nation into ſome effeminacy; and occaſioned the loſing of much of thoſe magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Improvements, which uſed always to be welcome to <hi>Engliſh</hi> minds. And this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till the late Civil War, which moſt influenced the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Rebells, made up of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks</hi> of the loweſt Ranks, and <hi>Plebeians:</hi> The ancient Gentry under Sequeſtration and Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (the glory of their loyalty) contenting themſelves to ſuffer for that Cauſe, which they could not retrive. And now lately opportunities have been mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred for our Soveraign to join with the moſt Chriſtian King, in order to the redeeming of the of the ancient Gallantry, which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94173:18"/>uſed to attend the Subjects of Monarchy, and hath been a long time fettered, and almoſt ſtifled, yet may now Exert it ſelf in the rebukes of the Treacheries of an unſaithful <hi>Anarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a Liberty (like that of our Neighbours) being (for the preſent) aſſumed, to uncage the mighty <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſouls, and to give them Elbow-room, in order to the great &amp; popular deſigns now abroad in the World; it may be true, that ſome looſeneſs perhaps may mix with that <hi>Liberty,</hi> and ſteal inſenſibly on ſome of the narroweſt and leſs wary Deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of popular Enterprizers.</p>
            <p>Yet this (if ſo) hinders not, but the preſent Age, (all circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces conſidered) is in fairer way
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94173:18"/>for improvement in all ſorts of honourable Science and heroick purpoſes, than any Age before us, ſome inſtances whereof may (perhaps) occurr in our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar notice of the <hi>Remarques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Methinks, your Adviſer was ſomewhat out while he Courts you ſometimes with mighty Encomiums, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges you to underſtand as much of <hi>true ſenſe and good breeding</hi> as moſt; yet he inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates the ſweet and prudent <hi>conduct</hi> of your <hi>Mother to overcome unpleaſant obſequiouſneſs;</hi> and the love of childiſh Liberties, as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to you not to leave the Country life. So that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what he ſays well of you ſometimes, at other times
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94173:19"/>he ſays as ill, or at leaſt, would have the World believe worſe of you; telling what mean Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion your <hi>Mother</hi> has of you, who would ſtill have you under her <hi>Regiment,</hi> fearing, yea, <hi>perplexed,</hi> that you will be debauched with the Vices of the Town: which is as much as to ſay, Sir, you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand as much as any one, but yet it is fit your Mother ſhould govern you ſtill, for you have not underſtanding enough to protect you from vicious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, Sir, you are beholding to him, pray thank him for nothing; He and your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have conſulted well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they are both willing you ſhould purſue noble Enterprizes, eſpecially thoſe of <hi>ſerving King
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94173:19"/>and Country;</hi> but it muſt not be at <hi>London,</hi> no, nor muſt you go thither to ſee if you have a <hi>King</hi> to ſerve, nor to learn how to <hi>ſerve</hi> him, or your Country.</p>
            <p>Theſe great Undertakings are to be accompliſhed under the <hi>Conduct</hi> and <hi>Regiment</hi> of your <hi>Mother,</hi> and to be taught you by inſpiration, and ſo upſtart Muſhrom-<hi>Hero</hi> in one Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light night in the Country.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, we had beſt have a care, we miſtake not, honeſt Country meaning: the <hi>Man</hi> ſays <hi>A life partly of Converſation, and partly of leiſure and retiredneſs, is moſt ſuitable to the affairs and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of men:</hi> and well is it ſaid too, <hi>i. e.</hi> Reading, Meditation, and Converſe, conduce much to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94173:20"/>make you a <hi>Hero,</hi> and <hi>to ſerve King and Country.</hi> Well ſaid in good ſooth, have at <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Arms</hi> now; Ah, but its <hi>Country</hi> Arts, and <hi>Country</hi> Arms, he means. Piſh, then 'tis no more but this; you are to <hi>ſend</hi> to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> I ſay <hi>ſend,</hi> for come not <hi>you</hi> here on pain and peril that <hi>will</hi> fall thereon; therefore, once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>ſend</hi> for the Statute Book, and the two famous Books of <hi>Daltons</hi> and <hi>Shepherds</hi> Juſtice of Peace Office, eſpecially that of <hi>Dalton,</hi> for there you will have all preſidents of <hi>Warrants, Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus's,</hi> and the whole Artillery of a learned Juſtice, there you will be furniſhed with ſo much skill as will make you be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a <hi>Hero. Judge</hi> to puniſh Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94173:20"/>againſt the Crown and Dignity of our Soveraign Lord the King, againſt the dignity of your Office and <hi>Heroſhip,</hi> who ſhall wickedly neglect to ſay <hi>Worſhipful</hi> at every word, and to do what you command right or wrong; by which means (aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Regiment and Conduct</hi> of your more learned <hi>Mother</hi>) you ſhall be abſolute Commander of all men and things that fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſwing of the learned part of you. You will alſo ſtrike ſuch awe into the minds of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Neighbours, and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, that they ſhall admire to hear you (over a Boull of <hi>Nogg</hi>) to tell News, like a little <hi>News-monger</hi> to arraign, trie, judge, and condemn the Conſultations, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94173:21"/>and Deſigns of King, Council, Parliament, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State; and (by the help of your Adviſers Letter) to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel at all things you are to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of, and make them wring their hands and wonder you are not made a Privy Counſellor, they not dreaming your <hi>Mother</hi> and her <hi>Secretary</hi> will not let you go to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe of <hi>Arts,</hi> (for we are to ſuppoſe all <hi>Arts</hi> to be in a <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Juſtice</hi>) be ſure you get a good and well-grounded Clerk, for that makes the Juſtice, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice the <hi>Hero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, Sir, you are to ſerve your <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> in way of <hi>Arms,</hi> which is the latter part of your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94173:21"/>
               <hi>Hero-ſhip.</hi> In order to that, you are, in Country <hi>leiſure</hi> and <hi>retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> to read that excellent and profound Piece, called <hi>The Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Grammar;</hi> which Book in ſhort time, with your <hi>Mothers</hi> Annotations, will make you (as to Arms) fit to be (in your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſers opinion) a Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; then you are to buy a great red Scarff with great gold Fringe, get your Clerk to put it on, on the ſide contrary to your Sword, that it may not hide the gilt Handle: ſummons your Company to appear before you on ſome convenient place on your Mannor, bid them <hi>ſtand</hi> to their Tackling, <hi>Face</hi> to the <hi>right,</hi> and then to the <hi>left,</hi> which is right againſt the <hi>Ale-houſe</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94173:22"/>(newly licenſed by you to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance your rent) give them a Barrel of Bear at a penny the Quart, receive their thanks by a Volley of ſhot, and go home like a mighty <hi>Hero</hi> returned from the Conqueſt of <hi>Granada,</hi> or the Siege of <hi>Rhodes.</hi> All this, I fanſie, Sir, your Adviſer reſerved for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Letter, after he had fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you from London, with the Snap-Dragons there, and (which Crowns all) the <hi>Converſe</hi> in the Country, with other ſuch like Hero's skilled in <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Arms,</hi> as aforeſaid, will exceedingly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your <hi>reading,</hi> and rivet theſe redoubted accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in your mind and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: whereas in <hi>London,</hi> ſilly, rude, villanous <hi>London,</hi> there are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94173:22"/>no men fit to converſe with, only ſome few who are <hi>retired,</hi> live to their <hi>own</hi> Conſciences, and are not good Companions.</p>
            <p>And this you may eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, Sir, if you believe what he ſays next, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Philoſophy is out of credit in this Age, and if he ſhould ſay otherwiſe, he fears, you would deſpiſe him for a Pedant.</hi> Now whether he <hi>fears</hi> you (in that) really, I know not, but to gratifie his fear, let him <hi>fear</hi> me, who (for ſo ſaying) do deſpiſe him as <hi>ſuch,</hi> for he now ſpeaks like one, <hi>that brute has the greteſt ſhare of,</hi> and bewrays that ignorance that meer <hi>Country Tuſcan</hi> is condemned to.</p>
            <p>How! <hi>Philoſophy out of credit!</hi> what! That <hi>Philoſophy</hi> which (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſays) found not <hi>Plato</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94173:23"/>Noble, but made him ſo: now <hi>out of credit!</hi> That Philoſophy <hi>out of Credit</hi> which made the Great Emperour <hi>Aurelius</hi> declare, That though he had no Reward among the Gods, nor honour among men, yet he was right glad to be a Philoſopher for the love of it ſelf. Strange news! And where out of Credit? In <hi>London</hi> be ſure; ah, and every where elſe, in the whole <hi>Age:</hi> then <hi>Country</hi> it ſeems has no <hi>Philoſophy</hi> neither. Well rhym'd <hi>Tutor,</hi> God-a-mercy good Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker. He perſwades you, Sir, <hi>Philoſophy is out of credit;</hi> no need of that: and ſo you are to be a Hero without it. Sir, I muſt tell you, if you had ſo little Wit as to believe this, you would never
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94173:23"/>have Wit enough to be a <hi>Hero.</hi> But being otherwiſe perſwaded of you; I ſhall endeavour to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive you, and inform you and your ignorant Adviſer too, that the two Notions of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and <hi>Languages</hi> compriſe <hi>all</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learnng. As to the laſt, never were thoſe attainments arrived at, as are at this preſent the <hi>Glory</hi> of this Age, this Nation, this great City. As for the <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern</hi> Languages, eſpecially the <hi>French,</hi> they are ſo familiar to us, that it's cauſe of Quarrel to your <hi>Man of Language,</hi> that they get place in our diſcourſes. As to the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Languages, I ſhall need to inſtance in no more than the <hi>Polyglot Bible,</hi> with the <hi>Lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> thereto; a performance ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94173:24"/>all Times, to the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting honour of thoſe worthy perſons, whoſe names add Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Work, and are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before it; and in ſpecial to that incomparable Linguiſt, who was the firſt in the Enterprize, and has ſurvived the reſt, the Reverend Dr. CASTLE, now <hi>Arabick</hi> Profeſſor in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in whom the Age is highly <hi>credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by his indefatigable Labours; and more highly <hi>diſcredited</hi> in that, that in ſlight to his Perſon and his Pains, in diſcouragement to future learned Attempts, no recompence has reached him, bearing any proportion with his merit, no, not with his charge in that ſingle invaluable Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94173:24"/>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Sir, As to <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> I fear the Man underſtands neither <hi>Name</hi> nor <hi>Thing.</hi> Good man, he never learned, perhaps, further than <hi>Barbara, Celarent,</hi> and ſo thought all Philoſophy conteined in <hi>Seton;</hi> and becauſe <hi>Raudolph</hi> calls him (unmannerly) <hi>Jack Seton,</hi> and Greaſie <hi>Jack Seton,</hi> he like a wiſe Philoſopher, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that <hi>Philoſophy</hi> is out of credit</p>
            <p>'Tis true, Sir, The meer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and diſputing part of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, the <hi>Mumpſimus</hi> of the old <hi>Stagerite</hi> and his <hi>Dogmata,</hi> are no more <hi>in credit,</hi> then as they contribute to <hi>practical</hi> knowledge and true <hi>Science,</hi> leading inquiries into the moſt inward receſſes of Learning, and thereby enlarging
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94173:25"/>the ſoul of man anſwerable to the deſign of ſuch an immortal being; which is the aim and honour of this preſent <hi>Age,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found the extream incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences which have bewitched the latter Ages, diſturbed the peace of Church and State, and prevented improvements in ſound Learning, even that <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputandi pruritus,</hi> idolized by men, whoſe only accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were, to be acute Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, dextrous Wranglers, and ſuch Philoſophy as that, and ſuch Philoſophers as they, I confeſs, are quite <hi>out of credit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sir, Had your Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſpent ſome of his <hi>long Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> at <hi>Arundel houſe, Greſham-Colledge,</hi> or any other of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94173:25"/>Societies of Learning now in <hi>London,</hi> he would not have put off Philoſophy, with an <hi>Out of Credit</hi> falſity. Nay, had he but ſeen a <hi>Book-ſellers</hi> ſhop once a Term; he might have ſeen the Catalogue of Books, products of the great and inſuperable indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and prodigious improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Philoſophers that are in <hi>Town;</hi> he might then have learned to tell you of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter buſineſs for Country diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements then <hi>riding after a Deer;</hi> that is, the improvements of Woods and Orchards, of culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating, impregnating, and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Lands by tillage and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, with a multitude more of inventions and branches of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, found out and enlarged
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94173:26"/>by the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> here, in their ſeveral ways and Societies, who in truth are the moſt real and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Benefactors to the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned World, that any Times have produced; and they are perſons (though of honour and renown, yet) of ſuch free, ſociable, and communicative conſtitutions, as diſpoſe them to diſtribute that knowledge with unlimited free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which they acquired with unwearied pains.</p>
            <p>And further, Sir, though your Friend willingly lays aſide, the conſiderations of <hi>Religion,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of ignorance, or what elſe, I know not, yet I can aſſure you, that our <hi>Philoſophers</hi> here do exceedingly contribute to the better part of Man, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94173:26"/>to the future ſtate. And, Sir, were you at <hi>London,</hi> and would not be frighted from Church with fear of a Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocket, you might hear <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> from the Pulpit, and conſtant preaching, not bettered by any dayes on this ſide the Apoſtles. And we here have <hi>leiſure</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiredneſs</hi> enough to read abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of excellent <hi>Philoſophy</hi> in the ſacred Pages, though <hi>Solomons</hi> great Body of <hi>Natural Philoſophy</hi> of Vegetables, from the Cedar to the Hyſop, is not yet come to light. Thus far, Sir, is <hi>Philoſophy out of credit;</hi> thus far, is your <hi>Tutor</hi> (upon his own challenge) to be <hi>deſpiſed as a Pedant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, Sir, He advances to a Home-ſpun Argument for a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94173:27"/>Country life; and that is, you ſhall have opportunities of <hi>read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hiſtory.</hi> Alas poor <hi>London!</hi> haſt thou loſt all thy <hi>Hiſtory?</hi> Hue and Cry, pray, after <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> Country <hi>Hero</hi> has robbed <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> of <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> Well it cannot be helped, <hi>Hiſtory</hi> muſt be read, and we muſt go into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to read it. Then, pray Sir, where do you dwell? that we <hi>Londoners</hi> may come and <hi>Hero-fie</hi> our ſelves with <hi>Hiſtory</hi> at your houſe. On my word, Sir, we have <hi>Philoſophy'd</hi> well indeed; we have raiſed a Spirit, which the <hi>out of Credit</hi> Folk call by the name of <hi>Dilemma.</hi> And thus he plagues us, either <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>ſurprize</hi> muſt have <hi>you</hi> by the bones, or your <hi>Tutor.</hi> If all we <hi>Londoners</hi> come
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94173:27"/>down to your Houſe to read <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> this will be <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>ſurprize</hi> to <hi>you:</hi> if you bring <hi>Hiſtory</hi> up to <hi>London,</hi> then there is <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>ſurprize</hi> to <hi>Tutor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Either you muſt bring it up, or ſend it up: if you <hi>bring</hi> it up, you will be you know what: if you <hi>ſend</hi> it up, you will loſe the means of being a <hi>Hero;</hi> and <hi>Tutor</hi> loſes his prime Argument. Lo, what a ſpirit is here now? he could go further too, if he were let alone. What work would this <hi>Fiend</hi> make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a Herd of Country <hi>Hero's?</hi> ſhrewd Work indeed!</p>
            <p>But, Sir, We <hi>Londoners</hi> and <hi>out of Credit Philoſophers,</hi> make no bones of ſuch <hi>ſpirits</hi> as theſe; Nay, they can conjure down
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94173:28"/>with three words, the verieſt <hi>Hobgoblin</hi> that ever ſcared poor Country <hi>Hero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come, Sir, Be not <hi>troubled</hi> nor <hi>ſurprized,</hi> this was no ſpirit, it was meerly a deluſion. We will not come to your Houſe for <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> nor any thing elſe, we have more plenty of all things here; in particular, more <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> more <hi>leiſure,</hi> more <hi>retiredneſs</hi> to read it, more and better converſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it; we do think it great pleaſure to <hi>ſee former Ages in the Glaſſes of Hiſtory.</hi> It is a part of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> it contributes to the making of a <hi>Hero,</hi> provided you reſt not in the <hi>Idea's</hi> of Things, but improve them into action, and confine them not to the <hi>ſcite</hi> of your Mannor.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94173:28"/>
            <p>And therefore, whereas your Adviſer prefers <hi>Hiſtory</hi> to <hi>perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance,</hi> becauſe, as he ſays, he <hi>that ſtands on high takes a more perfect account of an agreeable ſhew, then he that makes one of the Train.</hi> I doubt he wants ſome of the <hi>Town</hi> Wit, for the Alderman that ſtood on a Steeple, ſaw more of the fierce Battail at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> then any one in it; yet, I take it, (with ſubmiſſion to better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) that Sir <hi>Charles Lucas</hi> was likelier to prove the greater <hi>Hero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ancient time, it was <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> praiſe; <hi>quod mores hominum multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vidit &amp; urbes.</hi> But now I perceive, by a new-found Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Doctrine, in order to make a Hero. It is better to read <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94173:29"/>Geography,</hi> or <hi>Oglebie</hi>'s <hi>Atlas,</hi> then to travel, to read <hi>Lucan</hi>'s <hi>Pharſalia, Fiſher</hi>'s <hi>York fight,</hi> or perhaps, the admirable piece be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, <hi>the Souldiers Grammar,</hi> then to be an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Souldier.</p>
            <p>Oh brave Country-Juſtice-Captain-Hero. But to proceed, Our Man of Argument having told the ill luck of meeting an idle Companion (and it ſeems he has met with as much of that ill luck, as any of his Time, the more the pity, and then having ſhaken off the <hi>Gentleman,</hi> as it ſeems he was, but of no <hi>breeding, underſtanding nothing above the Breeches.</hi>) He mounts, and now <hi>baloo</hi> for the Country, upon the ran-dan, hey for the Country,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94173:29"/>oh brave Country. Sir, there you will have delight in the <hi>fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Horſe, purſuit of a Deer,</hi> variety of ſports, <hi>along the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Foot-cloths of Nature,</hi> you'l <hi>ſleep</hi> quietly, and not <hi>miſs of Idaea's to form you glorious Dreams;</hi> and what then? then all this <hi>is better then hunting a little Wench,</hi> (or a great one either) then <hi>beating the Watch, or breaking Glaſs win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,</hi> loſing a <hi>great quantity of Guinies,</hi> or <hi>playing away a Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> Oh wonderful! and is it ſo indeed? what follows? what? then by authentick conſequences of Country <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> Hunting, Walking, Sleeping, and Dreaming in the Country, will make you a Hero, and going to <hi>London</hi> will make you a Rogue.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94173:30"/>
            </p>
            <p>Sure this man has burnt his ſhins at your Fire, and therefore you muſt remove your Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, ſince we are on the <hi>beautiful Foot-cloths of Nature,</hi> and places of Sports, let's have a Verſe of Diſcourſe of <hi>Hunting.</hi> And as to that, (though prophane <hi>Eutopians</hi> think it unworthy to be uſed of Free men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reject it to their Butchers, to which Office they deſign their Bond-men, accounting Hunting the vileſt and moſt abject part of Butchery, eſpecially that Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which is for pleaſure only. Yet) we that are Philoſopher-Hiſtorians, do read of <hi>Xenophon</hi> (a better Philoſopher then any in <hi>Eutopia,</hi> which place for that,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94173:30"/>is worſe then <hi>London,</hi> for my Lord Major here keeps Hounds) how he commended Hunting to <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and called it a gift of the Gods, firſt beſtowed on <hi>Chiron</hi> for his doing Juſtice, and by him taught unto the old Hero's and Princes; and we at this day take it for a lawful Paſtime, befitting any man of what degree ſoever, and we take it withal, that the skill of well ordering a Pack of Hounds, may prefer a man to be my Lord Majors <hi>Dog-keeper,</hi> but never make him a <hi>Hero;</hi> but I'le tell you one thing, Sir, which your Adviſer never told you, perhaps never knew, <hi>viz.</hi> that if (with the <hi>London</hi> Philoſophers) you ſhall inquire into the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cauſes and grounds of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94173:31"/>what manner of <hi>effluviums</hi> or <hi>bodikins</hi> are left by the Hares foot on <hi>Natures Foot-cloth,</hi> how retained there for a good ſpace of time, how received into the ſents of the Hound, directed thereby, and by a natural impulſe to purſue poor <hi>Wats</hi> to death; you would out-do all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Hero's, and <hi>dream</hi> ſuch <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dreams,</hi> as <hi>Artemidorous</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of, <hi>formed of ſuch Idaea's</hi> as attend <hi>London Philoſophers.</hi> And this (indeed lo) is far better then keeping ſuch rude Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as Tutor, by <hi>long experience,</hi> has found out to reproach <hi>London</hi> with, and whereof the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> are wholly ignorant.</p>
            <p>Advance we next to a <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> you <hi>muſt marry,</hi> ay, marry
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94173:31"/>Sir, <hi>Ergo,</hi> you muſt not go to <hi>London;</hi> why not to <hi>London?</hi> ay, and for that purpoſe too; where ſo many Country heirs meet with Fortunes, who repair the Cracks of their ancient Families, add to others more mean, and are acceptable to the beſt. Oh, but Sir, if you go thither you will ſpoil your Inſtruments of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and never be able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue poſterity to ſucceed you in your Mannors, and Country-Heroſhip.</p>
            <p>Sir, This man it ſeems knows you <hi>Intus &amp; in cute;</hi> you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to a ſad fate, and good Sir <hi>Nativity-caſter</hi> has ſo decreed it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But why <hi>marry</hi> juſt now? he knows beſt, if he judges of you by himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:94173:32"/>
            <p>But (in earneſt Sir) I approve not too early marriages, as well for St. <hi>Pauls</hi> reaſons againſt all marriages, as for hindrance of Poſterity: yet (in good deed) if the caſe be ſo with you, that by traduction you inherit a conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution big with inclination of that cogency, as you <hi>muſt</hi> marry, or do <hi>like</hi> it; (and to the point he ſeems to ſpeak as knowingly, as dogmatically.) Then <hi>Marry,</hi> only get your Tutor (as prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive) to poſtil on the Hiſtory of <hi>Piramus</hi> and <hi>Thisbe,</hi> and lecture to you well thereon. But, Sir, how will this project conduce to the making you a Hero? for Marriage (they ſay) is a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to ſuch ends. Come, Sir, that's a miſtake, as i'le plainly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94173:32"/>make out by <hi>Philoſophical Hiſtory,</hi> as clear as the Sun; and now I think on't, it's the only <hi>Country trick</hi> to make you a <hi>Hero.</hi> One <hi>Vibius Rufus</hi> married <hi>Tullies</hi> Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and bought <hi>Caeſars</hi> Chair, to get the eloquence of the one, and the Power of the other, and when he had done all this, no doubt but he was a perfect Hero. Now, Sir, you being an accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed young Gentleman, and rich, may with your Adviſers help, <hi>marry</hi> thus, and be a Hero in a trice: if this won't do't, you muſt try ſome other ways; only come not at <hi>London,</hi> wicked <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> for Aſtrology ſake: ay, and the <hi>round ſum of ready money</hi> ſake; which is all condemned to the Cheats and Pick-pockets, if you
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94173:33"/>come at <hi>London.</hi> Was not your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſer, pray Sir, one of the <hi>Rump-Parliament?</hi> and argued Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy out of doors, on pretence that <hi>Kings</hi> have ſome times ill Counſellors? May I be ſo bold, Sir, Pray where do <hi>you</hi> dwell? I hope not near <hi>Banſted-Downs, New-Market,</hi> or <hi>Salisbury Plain,</hi> nor near a Market, a Fair, a City, or Town-Corporate: for on my word, lewd People frequent ſuch places, and many <hi>round ſums of ready money</hi> have been loſt there, and many a <hi>fair Manor</hi> morgaged. Well, Sir, if you were (indeed) born when all good Stars turned their backs on you, as is reported, I ſhould not adviſe you to uſe the <hi>manly exerciſe of riding after a Deer,</hi> fot I knew one who broke
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94173:33"/>a Horſe neck riding after Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, and I have heard many with as little a matter have broke their own necks, therefore you muſt look to your Hits in the Country alſo, unleſs the <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of your Mother be there a <hi>Charm</hi> againſt all <hi>Ill-lucks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, Sir, After a Croſs-Caper or two (by the help of fatal <hi>muſt</hi>) over the heads of ſome airy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of his, (and he ſeems to have many of ſuch acquaintance, and if he can leap over all their heads ſo, he is a nimble Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.) He attacques the <hi>Poets</hi> of the <hi>Town</hi> with all his might: have at the <hi>Poets,</hi> Heroick <hi>Poets,</hi> Dramatick <hi>Poets,</hi> and all this to make you a Hero. Sir, you <hi>muſt</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:94173:34"/>not acquaint your ſelf with <hi>Poets,</hi> nor read <hi>Poetry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, The man ſhould have done well to have inſtanced in any Age of the World, wherein Poetry was not in high eſteem, as well Heroick as Dramatick, <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſays that the reading of <hi>Virgil</hi> will make a man more honeſt then all the Precepts of Philoſophers, divine Mr. <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> ſays,
<q>
                  <l>A verſe may find him, who a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon flies,</l>
                  <l>And turn Delight into a Sacrifice.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Macedonian Amintas</hi> gave to <hi>Cherilus</hi> (a mean Poet) the value of an Angel for every Verſe, and our K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. for a few Pſalms
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94173:34"/>turned into <hi>Engliſh</hi> Metre, made <hi>Sternhold</hi> Groom of his Privy Chamber. <hi>Virgil, Homer, Lucan, Plautus, Terence, Horace,</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimire,</hi> (to name no more) for Heroick, Dramatick, and Lyrick, have always been, and ſtill are of great eſteem in all Ages and places. It pleaſed the holy Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to leave ſome Books of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ in Metre. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> was well acquainted therewith, and made good uſe too of the Heathen Poets, witneſs his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of <hi>Epimenides,</hi> 1 <hi>Tit.</hi> 12. <hi>Menander,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 15.33. and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Acts</hi> 17.28. and I fanſie he deſigned a Verſe of his own, <hi>James</hi> 1.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for I refer to the Greek Teſtament, and on the former Citations <hi>Eraſmus</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:94173:35"/>ſays, <hi>Plures ſine dubio legerat bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Paulus poetas quam quos recita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, &amp; recitando aliquos laudavit omnes.</hi> Sir, is not your Adviſer all this while a wiſe man to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt Poetry, on behalf whereof a Volume might be written; with as little ingenuity he falls foul on the Poet, and what is his fault? The Poet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves placing a praepoſition at the end of a ſentence, and falſe Grammar; which is a fault un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable, for Hero's <hi>are not to ſpeak with ſuch exactneſs;</hi> Silly man, the Poet ſpoke to Poets, not to Country Hero's. But he had heard perhaps how King <hi>James</hi> rebuked <hi>Gundamore</hi> for ſpeaking falſe Latine, and how <hi>Gundamore</hi> anſwered, that he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94173:35"/>ſpoke Latine like a King, and the King ſpoke Latine like a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, and from that excuſe in jeſt, he has raiſed an Argument in earneſt, that an Hero is not to ſpeak Grammar, and ſo <hi>Poet Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reat</hi> is killed on the leg, and all Poets in him.</p>
            <p>And why (good Sir Adviſer) is any to be reviled for the exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his skill? It is the firſt time ſure, that any one was made culpable for being without fault. Well, he will not leave Poet ſo, on he goes with another Thruſt; <hi>What does this</hi> (dramatick Poetry) <hi>ſignifie to the practical vertue of a Gentleman?</hi> Sure the man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo ignorant, as he ſeems, no body (though but eaſily skil'd in Learning) but can give ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94173:36"/>anſwer to the Queſtion, however, can ſay it <hi>ſignifies</hi> more then his <hi>manly exerciſe of riding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Deer.</hi> But (to wave com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon things) I can tell him, that I have been ſeveral times at a Play of that excellent Poets framing, whom he would revile, and I will maintain, there was more practical Divinity in it, then in ſeveral Country Sermons I have heard.</p>
            <p>Well, Sir, after a great deal of Billingſgatry againſt Poets, particularly againſt one of the beſt that ever <hi>England</hi> bred; he grows weary of him in good time, and fairly concludes, that the ſame man is of good life; his fault being (as it ſhould ſeem) he is a Poet; and Poets are guilty
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94173:36"/>of ſeveral faults beſides, <hi>ergo,</hi> my Lord Majors Huntſman is an undoubted Hero. And now for damned Poet, a full thruſt ſhall ſtrike him to the heart. Poets are guilty of <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> I fear he miſtook himſelf, and by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm</hi> meant <hi>Polytheiſm,</hi> for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, Modern Poets uſe <hi>Dii</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Deus,</hi> following ſtill the Dialect of the Heathen roguiſh Poets, which muſt needs be an unpardonable Crime. But what if the Heathen Poets in that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Idiom of the Writer of the Pentateuch, in his <hi>Elohim,</hi> (and it's thought that <hi>Ovid</hi> had ſeen thoſe Books) that Crime is become none. <hi>Atheiſm</hi> ſtill ſticks by their rib; as for example, ſome of the old Poets differed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:94173:37"/>about the Creation of the World; Pray which of them did ſo? He <hi>dubs Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> Poets, and then condemus them for <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> and through them all <hi>Poets</hi> to this day are under that ſentence.</p>
            <p>It is to be feared there are in the World too many <hi>practical Atheiſts,</hi> God bleſs the Adviſer, for the Ignorant are <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and 'tis the <hi>Fool</hi> ſaid in his heart you know what, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but indeed, I hardly believe that he can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in any one Modern Poet or other, that is in Judgment an Atheiſt, or that holds in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>the concourſe of Atoms by an undeſigning impetuous chance to make a World;</hi> for if they believe not <hi>Moſes,</hi> they will give credit
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94173:37"/>to <hi>Ovid;</hi> well but the Town Poets are Atheiſts, ay that they are, no matter why or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. I perceive Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> has diſpleaſed your Tutor, Sir, and there is no more to be ſaid, and ſo much for <hi>Atheiſm</hi> in Poets. Another fault, like it, is at hand; and that is a fault of <hi>Poets</hi> too, prophane <hi>Poets,</hi> who believe <hi>mankind has ſuffered in nothing more then in the reſtraints of Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, and ſo it's deplorable that the contempt of Wedlock is grown com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; and the next great ſubject of their Diſcourſe is the diſhonour of Women, and they believe there were never any honeſt Women but thoſe who lived ſolitarily, and were never attacqued by a powerful Courtſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a great many ill quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94173:38"/>had the perſons with whom this man was acquainted? what, vilifie Wedlock and diſhonour Women? O grievous! I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, Sir, I take it to be a fault, not of the leaſt magnitude; and now I think on't, I have heard of ſome ſhallow-brain'd fellows (pretenders to Poetry) who have thrown about <hi>Lampoons</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> to their followers, who at Coffee houſes and Taverns vent the Ware; this is done in the Country too, according to their little Wit. But, Sir, Theſe are not reckoned among the <hi>Poets,</hi> but <hi>Poetaſters,</hi> the true <hi>Poets</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and frequent not ſuch places, deſiring their Works ſhould ſavour of the <hi>oyl</hi> rather then the Wine: and they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94173:38"/>hold <hi>Marriage</hi> a <hi>ſacramental</hi> at leaſt; and for <hi>Women,</hi> they think them the Glory of the preſent Age, as far tranſcending the Mold and Materials of former Times, as the other improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Age exceeds for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and as much as any of that Beloved Sex exceeds in vertuous Accompliſhments, ſo much the more does ſhe attract to her ſelf their Honour and Regard. Yet becauſe it is ſo poſitively aſſerted that <hi>Wedlock</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> are diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected by ſome, I have been thinking who they are, and how they came hither. It ſeems, they are <hi>naughty</hi> men who diſ-eſteem Women; and I fear, 'tis <hi>naughty</hi> Women gives the occaſion; but both are in <hi>London,</hi> and how
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94173:39"/>came they there? were it not, Sir, for your Adviſers <hi>Atheiſm</hi> it might be thought that <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſent them hither by an <hi>impetuous chance;</hi> but I am not of that mind I aſſure you. And now, Sir, we are diſcourſing of <hi>Wedlock, Women,</hi> and <hi>Breeding, &amp;c.</hi> there comes a Story into my head, which, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, you nor your Tutor never met in the courſe of your reading Hiſtory; It has ſomething in it of all thoſe matters, and though it be ſomewhat long, you may bear with it, for it was bred and born in the Country, and in the Country reſolves to die.</p>
            <p>There was a <hi>man,</hi> who was an <hi>old man,</hi> his name was <hi>Proſper Richman,</hi> and he was a rich man, had a plentiful number of Acres,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94173:39"/>and a goodly Manor-houſe, and a round ſum of ready mony. He was of an ancient Family, as old as <hi>Meum &amp; Tuum;</hi> his Wife was the daughter of one Mr. <hi>Scrape,</hi> of Family equal, if not before the other; and a good Houſwife ſhe was, though not <hi>one</hi> of ten of that breed proves ſo. And theſe two by a ſleight they had uſed, had ſeven Sons and three Daughters; the eldeſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was crooked, witty, but ill-natured; the ſecond was han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtreight, but conſumptive; the third was very hanſome, very young, but ſomewhat ſilly.</p>
            <p>Theſe three Daughters (with the help of <hi>round ſums of ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> and the reputation of thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Parents, were diſpoſed of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94173:40"/>in marriage to three rich Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try heirs, who were appointed to their marriages at the ſecond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview, their Parents having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made the Matches.</p>
            <p>The Husband of the eldeſt, after ſome repititions of Loves Encounters had allayed his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, began to entertain mean thoughts of his <hi>Spouſe;</hi> and ſhe being by day froward and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, he accounted her the latter part of the night to be but a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Bones crowdeed together into a Poke, and ſet upon two ſtilts, and ſo thought he was in Bed with a Skeleton: thence took a diſtaſte at her, and grew deſirous to be acquainted with the perfections of that <hi>Sex.</hi> In order to that, following his eyes,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94173:40"/>he fixes his fanſie with ſome ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs on <hi>Mal.</hi> the daughter of Mr. <hi>Boniface,</hi> Parſon of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; and at laſt obtained op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to beſtow on her ſome <hi>Country Innocence.</hi> Afterward on ſome Tenants daughters, and by and by on his Maids one after another; inſomuch that Aprons growing ſhort among them, he ſends them <hi>toties quoties</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> to ſome grave Woman, who in a Moneths time can make any Apron as long as it was before, and you cannot ſee where it was mended. And (would you think it) by this doing between his Age of 20 years when he married, and 30, he ſent to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> on that errand a ſcore of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with their Appurtenances.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:94173:41"/>
            </p>
            <p>As to the ſecond Daughter, her husband liked her pretty well by day, but by night, being continually diſturbed of his reſt with her coughing, and in his ſtomach, with the unſavoury odors which aroſe from her brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and the great lumps of rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Lungs which ſhe belched forth on the ſpitting ſheet, and ſome time on the Chamber: Troth, he in ſhort time, loathed her, took ſuch Courſes as t'other had done, and then did, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed this <hi>Town</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> O unhappy <hi>London!</hi> with more then the other had done by five.</p>
            <p>He that married the third, (which was for ſymetry of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and excellent features very
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:94173:41"/>beautiful) promiſed himſelf great felicity in the enjoyment of her: but it fell out, that (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her tender years) that which in riper perſons makes a pleaſureable Impreſſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets (beſides what elſe) an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared affection to her, ſignified the clear contrary; and indeed, to him, ſeemed puniſhment for marrying one not yet 15 years of Age: ſo ſhe wanting Wit and natural courage, and fancying that conjugal Rites would never be performed at eaſier rates, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refuſed, or refuſed to aſſiſt thoſe embraces which are the life of married ſtate: wanting alſo knowledge in houſhold affairs, carriage, and diſcourſe, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as little entertainment for
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94173:42"/>her Husband by day as by night. Whereupon he takes Pet, eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes other ſocieties, grows informed of the others vices, and by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature is prompted to the lewd courſes of other Brethren in Law; and ſends the ſame way on the ſame errand, no leſs then nine in two years; and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny after that I heard not, nor have I heard of the ſum total of the reſt: but we may gueſs them to be a jolly number on a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>pro ratâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (which is remarkable on this third Daughters part, beyond the reſt) ſhe became jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of her Husband, and her Husband careleſs of her. And this news flying into the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Villages, the Country, ſturdy
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94173:42"/>young Fellows reſorted to her; and what out of ſpight to her Husband, what out of itch, made, and claw'd, by others not hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſhe admitted offers, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them into her Embraces, and I know not what, fanſied the motions, became affecter of Game, a lover of any but her Husband, and in fine, was in fair to make as many Rogues, as he did Whores.</p>
            <p>Theſe Daughters of this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Family being thus (by the aid of great Portions) provided for, the good old Gentleman prides himſelf in the Companies of his goodly number of Sons, fancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one to be a ſeventh, a Conjurer, a Fortune-teller, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician, Cunning-man, or (at
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94173:43"/>leaſt) no Fool. He kept a Houſe like the <hi>Old Courtier of the Queens,</hi> or <hi>the Queens old Courtier.</hi> He had all his ſons ſet about his Table, with their Hats on their heads, as they did at all times in Fathers preſence, though two of them were under 20. years of Age. Theſe Sons could ſcarce read, or write their names well; And that hapned thus; when the eldeſt was very young, and intended for School, a Puritan came to the good old Father, and told him of a pious Book called the <hi>Confeſsions of good Auſtin,</hi> which he had often read, and found that one of the firſt great offences that Holy man repented of after his Converſion, was robbing of an Orchard, which he was enticed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:94173:43"/>to by the wicked ſolicitations of his Fellow-Scholars at a Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar School; therefore, worthy Sir, (quoth he) ſend not your Son to School, for he <hi>will</hi> learn to rob Orchards, and then be forced to do Penance in old Age, and that before the uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Formaliſt of his Pariſh, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Idolatrous Rubrick.</hi> At which diſcourſe there hapned to be preſent a Paedagogue, who took up the Cudgels in defence of <hi>School-Education,</hi> uſing many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to that purpoſe: and for anſwer to the Orchard buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, told of one of great <hi>Natural Wit,</hi> who bewailed his not going to a Free-School, for many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; in particular, for that he miſſed the opportunities, of <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:94173:44"/>Orchards, whereby he might have learned the Arts of Scaling of Walls, beſieging of Towns, Approaches, Retreats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at which the old Gentleman ſtopped him, ſaying, Hold Sir, I like not you, nor your <hi>Man of Natural Wit</hi> neither; who ſeems to me to be a man void of Grace, eſpecially in compariſon of this <hi>Godly</hi> man, whoſe directions I will follow; who hath informed me from the ſame <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that <hi>Grace</hi> is enough, without the prophane Learning of the Heathens. And from that time he reſolved againſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and provided for his Sons (according to the Country Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation) a Huntſman, with a Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of Blood-Hounds, Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds, Beagles, and Tarriers.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94173:44"/>A Falkoner with Sparrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hawks, Lanners, Taſſels, and Goſs-hawks. A Warrener with Tumblers and Lurkers, beſides other implements of his Art. Another Servant who attended the Grey-hounds, and Setting-Dogs: an Archer for the Long-Bow, Croſs-Bow; and had the skill of Gun and Stalking-Horſe too, and all his Materials and Inſtrnments of Game, were kept always at hand. A Fiſherman uſed his time well about the Ponds, Dams, and Meers, in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the Table with moſt ſorts of Freſh-water Fiſh, and made it pleaſant in the taking them, with Angles, Trolls, Snares, Nets, and other Engines. There was alſo a Billiard-Table, Shovel-board,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94173:45"/>Cheſs-board, Cards, Dice, Nine-Pins, and they that would might alſo play at Nine holes, or Span Counter. There was deſigned a Tennis Court to be built, but one (like your Adviſer, Sir) came and told, that it was uſed at <hi>London,</hi> and that naughty people uſed to come thither, and to go from thence to naughty places, which ſpoiled the project, <q>So ſtrange a thing is a prejudic'd mind, as if a Tennis Court were not leſs noxious then Cards and Dice, yet ſuch is the fooliſh admiration of perſons, That Errors are eſpouſed, for the Authors ſake,</q> and ſome ſuch weighty reaſon, pulled down the Tennis Court at <hi>New-market.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to our buſineſs again, Sir,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:94173:45"/>
               <hi>i. e.</hi> to the Story of the ſeven Sons, who you ſee were provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for to make Country <hi>Hero's,</hi> far beyond what your Adviſer has mentioned to you.</p>
            <p>Sir, Theſe young Gentlemen every day made uſe of ſome of theſe divertiſements, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs became good proficients therein; only <hi>George,</hi> one of the youngeſt, often ſtaid at home, pretending to break his Faſt with <hi>Curds and Cream, Freſh Butter,</hi> and <hi>New brown Bread, Butter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milk,</hi> or <hi>Whey;</hi> and doing often ſo, the eldeſt Brother <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> fanſied the <hi>Dairy</hi> afforded ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more pleaſant than what he knew, and ſo watched <hi>George</hi> on a time, and through a Creviſs perceived that <hi>George</hi> had found
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94173:46"/>out a <hi>Recreation</hi> not provided for by the <hi>Old man;</hi> and that was, to help <hi>Tydy</hi> the <hi>Dairy</hi> Maid to Churn; which Churning was done after ſuch a manner, as made <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Teeth to water, as if <hi>Buttermilk</hi> or <hi>Whey</hi> had a Spring in his mouth. All this <hi>Ezekiel</hi> kept to himſelf, and when <hi>George</hi> was a Hunting then he helped to Churn with <hi>Tydy;</hi> which pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge he obtained, to keep Counſel and (on the ſame ſcore) every one of the Brothers had their turns, and I think <hi>ſhe</hi> was well helped to Churn; inſomuch that by over-labouring, or by one thing or another, the poor Wench grew ſick a mornings, and you might ſee her red Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings half way up her legs, which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:94173:46"/>made her ask leave to go home to her Friends; and being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, was conveyed to <hi>London,</hi> at the charge of the Eldeſt Brother only; for he ſtood on his reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as heir of the Family, and in hopes of preferment courted ſecrefie: but <hi>George</hi> and the reſt, as they had no more then younger Brothers expectancies, ſo expected no diſparagement by a younger Brothers Frolick.</p>
            <p>And from that time ('tis ſtrange ſuch a thing ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in <hi>Innocent Country</hi>) there was not a Maid-ſervant could ſtay in that Family above ſix Moneths, what became of them I know not; but it is ſaid that a great many Women Folk went from that houſe to <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:94173:47"/>
            <p>Well, Sir, By this time Age gave the old Gentleman an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of removing to t'other World: ſo he ſent for the Parſon whoſe name was <hi>Lionel Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> who made his Will; by which his wife was made <hi>Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix,</hi> and all his Mannors, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, was bequeathed to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son; he gave to his ſecond, third, and fourth Son 100 <hi>l per annum</hi> a piece, during life; and to the other three younger Sons he gave 1000 Marks a piece, and made the ſaid Parſon, and one Mr. <hi>Getmore,</hi> a Neighbour, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perviſors, deſiring them in all love to be aiding and aſſiſting to his ſaid Sons, with friendly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and ſo he died, was buried,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:94173:47"/>and forgotten: After whoſe death, the heir grew <hi>Houſe-keeper,</hi> the old Gentlewoman doing all the Offices of a Wife (excepting what <hi>Tydy</hi> uſed to do.) The Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo (paying for their Boards) continued their former Courſes, <hi>went to Bed early, ſlept quietly, by the help of Idaea's had glorious dreams, roſe before the Sun, ſported on the beautiful Foot-cloths of Nature;</hi> and twenty things more, beſides waſting their Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Soon after it happened, one <hi>Thomas Lender</hi> of <hi>London</hi> a <hi>Pawn-Broker,</hi> died of the <hi>Plague</hi> inteſtate, leaving a Widow of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 35 years of Age, after whoſe death, ſhe cauſed her husbands Goods to be <hi>Inventoried</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſed;</hi> in which <hi>Inventory</hi> was
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:94173:48"/>mentioned in Bonds 5000 <hi>l.</hi> in the Shop, in Jewels, Plate, Watches, Books, and other Goods 5000 <hi>l.</hi> in <hi>toto</hi> 10000 <hi>l.</hi> ſhe being afright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Diſeaſe, which had taken away her Husband, removed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Country for a time, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened into this Mr. <hi>Richman</hi>'s Town; and growing acquainted with this Family, by diſcourſe was diſcovered, that her late Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Mother was of the Family of the <hi>Scrapes,</hi> and ſo a kind of affinity was ſtarted between her and them; and improved ſo far, as ſhe was deſired to reſide (du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her ſtay in the Country) at that Houſe, where ſhe had not long been, ere the Widow impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the value of her Eſtate, which took preſently with the old
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94173:48"/>Woman, who could not reſt till ſhe had engaged a Treaty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and her Son <hi>Ezekiel</hi> for a Marriage; and though the Widow had nothing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend her to his acceptance, but her wealth, yet that Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment improved by an <hi>indulgent Mothers</hi> deſcants, prevailed for a Match, which was ſoon diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; and the joy that the hopes of this <hi>round ſum of mony</hi> brought, occaſioned open Houſe-keeping for a moneth, and publick En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment for all comers, which coſt at leaſt 1000 <hi>l.</hi> ſoon after which Jollities ended, the Bride and Bridegroom went to <hi>London</hi> with purpoſe to remove the Treaſure into the Country; but when they came there, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:94173:49"/>ſome wiſer than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Appriſers, it was found that the Jewels, Plate, and other Goods, were indeed of the value of 5000 <hi>l.</hi> but they were pawned but for 1500 <hi>l.</hi> and the ſums mentioned in the Bonds, were indeed of the value, but by the conditions of thoſe Bonds, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared that the Bonds were given only for further ſecurity, for the ſame Moneys lent on the Goods; ſo ſhe was worth in truth but 1500 <hi>l.</hi> whereof 1000 <hi>l.</hi> was ſpent on the Weddingſolemnities.</p>
            <p>This angered good <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to the heart, and his old Mother too, who curſed <hi>London</hi> Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and adviſed the younger Sons to ſtay in the Country ſtill, leſt they alſo ſhould be cheated;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:94173:49"/>not conſidering this Trick was in the Country, and lay at their own door, through want of Wit and Conſideration, which the Wit of the Town would have obviated.</p>
            <p>The new married man want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Whetſtones of his Love, Beauty, and Money, neglected his Wife, even to hatred, returned to the ways his Brother <hi>George</hi> had taught him, and followed that courſe, till he and his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had almoſt emptied the Country of Maids. His Wife not being in his debt, received as good Viſits as he made; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them both, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Houſe ſeemed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved: a mixt concourſe of Viſitants conſtantly filling the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:94173:50"/>Beds, emptying the Bottles (for they were uſed alſo to drive away diſcontent) the Buttery, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury; ſo that the name of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> began to ſeem improper for perſon and place.</p>
            <p>The younger Sons following the way of their Education, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding grave Superviſors advice) became ſo clear-ſighted as to ſee to the furtheſt end of their Portions, without the help of a Teloſcope; the Annuities being deeply dipped to Mr. <hi>Get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> one of the <hi>Superviſors,</hi> by the procurement of his Partner, the truſty Parſon, on whom, and at whoſe Houſe, much of the money was ſpent; and the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of money, in like manner was three parts ſpent.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:94173:50"/>
            <p>Whereupon they conſidered, that they were of good extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, having pure and uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bloud leaping in their veins, that they had been educated in the way of Country <hi>Hero's,</hi> that univerſal expectation claimed from them things generous and heroick, and how to carry on noble Enterpriſes, and to arrive at great and honourable ends, with a remnant of Eſtate, in the <hi>Deſarts</hi> of the World (for ſo they now call the Country) by the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling vanities of ſports (ſo now they called the Country divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) muſt be thought on: and without much ado, labour, or ſtudy, it was concluded, (and ſo ſoon as one would think it was dictate of Nature) to <hi>London</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:94173:51"/>they muſt go, and try their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; and to <hi>London</hi> they went, and not having fortune enough, or good enough, to purchaſe the friendſhip of <hi>Court</hi> nor Learning enough to join with the Societies of <hi>Learning,</hi> nor money enough left to fall into <hi>Commerce,</hi> nor courage enough to take up <hi>Arms;</hi> they furniſh themſelves with <hi>Peruches</hi> and <hi>Pantaloons,</hi> and find out the <hi>Waſtcoateers</hi> formerly ſent from the Country for the better ſhaping of their Bodies, who had improved themſelves by this time into the exactneſs of ſome eminent <hi>Vices,</hi> eſpecially of that which they brought from the Mannor of <hi>Richman,</hi> and now were become able to inſtruct their <hi>Country</hi> Gallants, and to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:94173:51"/>bring them acquainted with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſuch as your grave <hi>Adviſer,</hi> Sir, has by <hi>long experience</hi> known, and has elaborately told you of, and ſo we leave them together, and there is an end of the <hi>Story.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, As ſoon as this <hi>Story</hi> was told <hi>me,</hi> I was thinking, that if it were duly conſidered in all its branches, and well <hi>weighed,</hi> it would be an anſwer to your <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſers</hi> Letter, without more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do; but it coming but now to my hands, I here inſert it.</p>
            <p>Sir, As for a <hi>Story</hi> where the Sons of <hi>Country Gentlemen</hi> have by good and proper Education, become true <hi>Hero's, Patriots</hi> of their Country, and poſſeſſing eminent ranks of Authority and Dignity; I take it needleſs, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:94173:52"/>you to <hi>Beloved Hiſtory,</hi> either in City or Country, from which may be collected Volumes of ſuch <hi>Hero's,</hi> exceeding <hi>Fox</hi>'s Book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and truer too. And (though the obliquities of the late Times have diſcouraged Learning to a great degree, and laid ſhackles on Gentlemens Parts and Eſtates, yet) ſince our Soveraigns return, it's obvious, that greater improvements have been made by the <hi>Scyons</hi> of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry in all Arts, in 12 Years, than in an hundred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, to the Letter again, and let us ſee more of the Town faults, and a <hi>great one</hi> riſes next; and that is, a <hi>Language</hi> (divers from the times of our Anceſtors)
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:94173:52"/>is in <hi>London</hi> uſed. <hi>Language</hi> ſaid he? Marry till now I took <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to ſpeak the beſt Language of all <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> to ſpeak the beſt Language except the univerſal one: but I am told otherwiſe now, this <hi>Age,</hi> this <hi>Nation</hi> is corrupt in its Language. A bold charge is it on the <hi>wiſeſt Age,</hi> and <hi>wiſeſt Nation,</hi> and where is the fault? in uſing <hi>French words;</hi> vile <hi>French,</hi> even vile <hi>French words,</hi> unworthy of the <hi>manly Language</hi> of <hi>Engliſh</hi> to uſe <hi>French words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure, this Man, Sir, has been ſtung with a Bee, and now loves no Honey. He has, perhaps, ſuffered under ſome diſtemper called <hi>French</hi> — and ſo will ſtarve, rather than eat <hi>Fricacie</hi> or <hi>Ragoo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:94173:53"/>
            <p>But a ſerious word, Sir, Our <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is that of thoſe <hi>Germans</hi> called <hi>Saxons,</hi> who poſſeſſed themſelves thereof, next preceding the <hi>Normans;</hi> and that Language was moſtly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllables, of which <hi>Radixes</hi> have ſince been made <hi>Compounds;</hi> and though it has been thought that from ſuch various Roots might ariſe <hi>Compound-words</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, and ſo no need of what is Foreign; yet in that <hi>Age,</hi> and that <hi>People, Knowledge</hi> was <hi>ſtinted,</hi> and few <hi>words</hi> would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs few things, and ſo no need was there of enlarging the <hi>Lingua,</hi> or opportunity for it. <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> tell us, that when the <hi>Normans</hi> expulſed the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> among the Clerks in Holy Orders, if one
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:94173:53"/>had learned the Grammar, every one wondered at him as a mighty Scholar.</p>
            <p>After that time Learning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to encreaſe, and by the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> came the <hi>French</hi> Tongue hither, and though they could not introduce <hi>their</hi> Laws, yet <hi>their</hi> Language they did, and put our <hi>Laws</hi> into it; by reading of which, and converſing with them, grew a mixture of Tongues with the <hi>French,</hi> which has been improved by a commerce more <hi>familiar</hi> with that Nation than with any other.</p>
            <p>And it's true, that in this laſt Age, wherein our Nation has out done all others in the ſuper-ſtructures of true Science, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral terms of Art have mixed with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:94173:54"/>our ordinary diſcourſes, which by reaſon of their eaſineſs to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, can hardly be avoided.</p>
            <p>And it's remarkable, that what words ſoever our Nation has adopted, they are moſt ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant of the things they expreſs, and ſo occaſion a ſuccinct and comprehenſive ſtile in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and Writing.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>old Dotage</hi> of keeping to our firſt Language, which was <hi>Teutonick;</hi> I would ask your <hi>Adviſer,</hi> Sir, to give me one inſtance of any People that does it. Let him look into <hi>Verſtegan</hi> for the Monoſyllables, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint with the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Low Dutch, Normay, Sweden, and Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and ſee if any of them retain the <hi>old Teutonick,</hi> and how much,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:94173:54"/>and how they differ from <hi>it,</hi> and among themſelves, and he ſhall ſoon find that every one of them, as well as we, do differ from the <hi>ſerious manly Language</hi> of our <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Anceſtors,</hi> as they are ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcituated in the ſeveral parts of their reſpective Nations; ſo do we in <hi>England.</hi> An inſtance whereof you may have in <hi>Verſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> who thereby anſwers himſelf in the <hi>whimſie</hi> your <hi>Adviſer</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from him.</p>
            <p>As one woul ſay at <hi>London,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I would eat more Cheeſe if I had it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Northern</hi> man ſays,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ay ſud eat mare Cheeſe gin ay hadet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:94173:55"/>
            <p>And the <hi>Weſtern</hi> man ſays,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chud eat more Cheeſe an chad it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be you Judge now, Sir, who ſpeaks beſt Engliſh, <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Country.</hi> And I challenge all his Country Hero's, who were never educated in <hi>London,</hi> to careſs you with an <hi>Harangue</hi> like that of his <hi>Remarques,</hi> which (as the matter is <hi>Romantick,</hi> ſo the ſtile <hi>Rhodomontade,</hi> ſufficiently laced with Foreign words, rude <hi>French</hi> and all) does amply turn upon himſelf, and ſilence the imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent complaint. And ſo much ſhall ſuffice to have been deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed concerning the <hi>old, ſerious, manly, Engliſh Language.</hi> Only I muſt not forget, that after his invectives againſt <hi>French,</hi> he
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:94173:55"/>kindly ſays, <hi>That Language is highly neceſſary to all that frequent Courts, and that have to do in the important affairs of the World.</hi> This ſtartled me, when he ſays, <hi>French</hi> Tongue is neceſſary to Courtiers, and thoſe <hi>concerned in important affairs,</hi> and yet not to you, whom he deſigned and adviſed to be a <hi>Hero.</hi> It made me recollect my ſelf, and conſider what a <hi>Hero</hi> is. I find the word is not <hi>Teutonick</hi> no more than <hi>Idaea, Chimera, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, Regiment,</hi> with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which are for this time deigned worthy to be the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidery of his Lines, and the Livery of his Pages. But I found out what uſually <hi>Engliſh</hi> men underſtand by this <hi>Remarqueable</hi> word <hi>Hero,</hi> and it happens to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:94173:56"/>be the very ſame, that the <hi>Greek</hi> word imports, <hi>viz.</hi> one who has attained to great Renown, by great Parts, Knowledge, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Archievements, in the ways of Arts, Arms, or other <hi>the important affairs of the World;</hi> to ſuch a one as this the <hi>French Tongue</hi> (it ſeems) is <hi>highly neceſſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, Sir, while he inveighs againſt the <hi>French Tongue</hi> to you, judge you what manner of <hi>Hero</hi> he would have you to be; you are to be a <hi>Hero,</hi> but the <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riums</hi> to it you muſt avoid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> told his Proſylites that he ſhould be like a great Ram with a great <hi>Fleece,</hi> and they ſhould be like little <hi>Fleas</hi> ſhroud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in his Fleece, and then he would give a jump into
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:94173:56"/>Paradice, and carry them with him. Juſt ſo, your Adviſer Sir, is to jump you into a <hi>Hero.</hi> You muſt abhor the <hi>French Tongue,</hi> not have to do in the <hi>important affairs of the World,</hi> nor <hi>frequent Courts,</hi> nor ſo much as ſee wicked <hi>London;</hi> but you <hi>muſt</hi> be a <hi>Hero,</hi> ay that you muſt; you <hi>muſt</hi> live in Ignorance, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like an uſeleſs <hi>Country Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> and King <hi>Oberon,</hi> at a <hi>lucky chance,</hi> ſhall <hi>ipſo facto</hi> Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſe you into a <hi>Hero:</hi> A <hi>chance</hi> indeed, like that the <hi>Pro-Conſul</hi> ſpake of to St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe of Judicial Aſtrology, viz. <hi>the force of chance diffuſed about in the nature of things, brings to paſs as foretold, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I muſt tell you it muſt be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:94173:57"/>a <hi>chance,</hi> and a very lucky one too, that will make you a <hi>Hero,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>means</hi> or <hi>indeavours.</hi> A Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Counſellor, Lord Lieutenant, a General, are not <hi>Hero's</hi> as <hi>ſuch,</hi> but as they are qualified to be <hi>ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Advance we two or three ſteps further, and there we ſhall meet your <hi>Remarquer,</hi> Sir, at the turn of a Corner, ready to ſcare you, as he ſcares Children in the <hi>Country,</hi> and cries don't go to <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>Tom Poker</hi> will get you and put you into his Pocket. <hi>You muſt write a Play.</hi> Sir, his deſign being to keep you in <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> and fright you with Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he might rather have ſaid, if you go to <hi>London,</hi> you muſt <hi>plead Cauſes,</hi> Anatomize humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:94173:57"/>paſs Fiery Trials with Prince <hi>Robert</hi> and Mr. <hi>Boil,</hi> in the Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this had been a <hi>noiſe</hi> able to ſcare a good chub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Country Fellow; or like <hi>Tays</hi> the Moving Clod, that ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>Tuſcan</hi> Ploughmen.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, notwithſtanding this Country Chancellors Decretal <hi>Muſts,</hi> I do aſſure you (on my credit) you are no more obliged to <hi>write a Flay,</hi> than your <hi>Marks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> was to write his Letter; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which may be accounted a bold undertaking, the ſucceſs being ſo hazardous.</p>
            <p>And ſince we are ſpeaking of writing Plays and Books, I <hi>muſt</hi> obſerve to you, that about the time your Letter was publiſhed, there was a <hi>Comedy</hi> acted at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:94173:58"/>in which (to ſee how good Wits may <hi>jump</hi>) was all the wit of the Letter, and a thouſand times more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There</hi> was a Country <hi>Hero</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a company of poor, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, brutiſh Boors (that word is Teutonick) drinking, ſotting, telling news, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning that great City called <hi>Ditto</hi> in the <hi>Gazette,</hi> and the miſerable eſtate of <hi>Poland:</hi> rayling at <hi>London,</hi> charging all the <hi>Blunderbuſſes</hi> and <hi>Granadoes</hi> of his Office, in defiance of all that ſhould laugh at an Ignorant-Juſtice-Captain of 2000 <hi>l. per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and hoped to be Deputy-Lieutenant: and, in ſhort, one, who by the help of a <hi>fierce</hi> Dap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-grey <hi>Mare,</hi> and an <hi>obſequious</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:94173:58"/>Setting Dog, judged himſelf a greater <hi>Hero</hi> than <hi>London</hi> ever ſaw.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Hero's</hi> name, Sir, was <hi>Hugh Clodpate</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> of an Ancient Family, known in all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>England,</hi> the Plays name was <hi>Epſom Wells.</hi> I adviſe you, Sir, to ſend up to <hi>London,</hi> for a Copy of it, for 'tis not yet printed; leſt it ſhould ſpoil the ſale of the <hi>Remarques,</hi> there is an ingenious Gentleman, by name Mr. <hi>Shad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> who may help you to it, and then you may compare the one with the other. I dare ſay the Author of one was not of the other, for the Play is a thing of great ingenuity: and there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother difference between the Play and the Book; for what the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:94173:59"/>
               <hi>Poet</hi> did in jeſt, this <hi>Epiſtler</hi> does in earneſt; that is to give a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand</hi> to ſome abſurdities of the <hi>Town,</hi> next, to render <hi>Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haters</hi> ridiculous.</p>
            <p>Sir, If you come to Town, and the worſt comes to the worſt, if you can't write a <hi>Play,</hi> you may write a ſilly Book, and ſwagger againſt them who can write <hi>Plays,</hi> and ſay, <hi>that this Phantaſtical neceſsity was impoſed upon you, and you were not obliged to bazard your abilities on ſuch ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of Fame and Humour:</hi> and ſo winding your ſelf up in a few wrathful ſheets, they become Armour of Proof againſt all <hi>London</hi> Foes, who will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently feel the ſmart of your fatal <hi>rap:</hi> as others (God wot) have
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:94173:59"/>done to their grief and ſorrow. Witneſs (in the next place) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy <hi>Inns of Court, unhappy,</hi> yea verily <hi>unhappy,</hi> in being the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the ill will of this mighty <hi>Hero-maker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, As to theſe contemptible Bodies, he is pleaſed to cut them in three Morſels, yet is able to devour them at one Bit.</p>
            <p>The firſt are the <hi>Practiſers of the Law,</hi> the <hi>Idaea of whoſe conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation (he ſays) is very Pedantick, and unpolliſhed, and in truth, not worthy of a Gentleman; concealing Truth, tiring out the Votaries of Juſtice, forcing Conſcience to truckle under the love of money, and having nothing agreeable to the Principle of nobleneſs.</hi> Pray, Sir, when you read this, did not you take this
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:94173:60"/>man to be <hi>Non-Compos?</hi> to have ſpent his time in a <hi>Colledge</hi> ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate between <hi>Biſhopſgate</hi> and <hi>Moorfields,</hi> thinking no man, but one touched in his <hi>Brain,</hi> could <hi>rave</hi> ſo formally, and render himſelf in ſuch prodigious Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, and prophane ſcurrilities; he ſeems to borrow the humour from a Modern Wrangler, who out of ſpight to the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> ſcolds at my Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of <hi>Practical Philoſophy:</hi> and againſt all <hi>Common Lawyers,</hi> becauſe <hi>Oldenbarnevelt</hi> (a Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian) was an Arminian in the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> ſo eager Wolves bark at the Moon, ſo mad Dogs bite all but mad Men.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, As for the Inns of Court, they have been and are at
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:94173:60"/>this day owned by all Foreigners and Domeſticks to whom they are known, as the moſt renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Societies, as well for the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion</hi> of the Law, as for the <hi>Law</hi> they profeſs, that the World has. And as to the perſons in <hi>higheſt</hi> Vogue, for their excellencie in that Science, (having by indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable induſtry ſubdued the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of their own Art, and by that made themſelves Maſters of the greateſt Reaſon and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which attends any other Body of Learning) can and do entertain their Vacations with inquiries into other parts of Knowledge, which with much eaſineſs do readily fall under their comprehenſion. And being ſo furniſhed, are alſo endued with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:94173:61"/>a ſtock of Prudence, that capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates them for a deportment an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the Circumſtances of Times, Places, and Perſons; whether it be in the more grave and reſerved way, which their Profeſſion, or other Knowledge, or the Societies of ſtrict men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges them to: or in the Paths that Men and Learning of lower Forms (called more generous and delightſome) leads them to. And he muſt be a great ſtranger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, who cannot inſtance in great Sages of our Common-Law, who have been eminent, even in the retired Walks of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Learning, that have deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed endeavours to the perfecting of the Works of Nature; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther improving Nature to the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:94173:61"/>beſt advantages of life, and the common benefit of mankind, as has been ſaid of them by ſome of ſufficient prejudice againſt that Profeſſion; and there are now being perſons of ſo general know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (not ſeaſonable to mention) as no other Society of ſingle Learning can parallel.</p>
            <p>Sure, Sir, This <hi>No-mans-friend,</hi> has had ſome ill luck at Law, he may have dealt in ſome crackt Title, or ingaged in ſome unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable ſuit, that would not hold Water; and becauſe his Lawyers could not <hi>Buoy</hi> him up in his undertakings, to't goes the Profeſſion; or perhaps ſome leſs thing may exaſperate a waſpiſh man, and make him buz. There was one <hi>Pawlet,</hi> who had vowed
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:94173:62"/>never to come to <hi>London;</hi> and being Defendant to a ſuit in Chancery, had the Court moved for a Commiſſion to anſwer in the Country, alledging for Cauſe, his Vow, of which <hi>affidavit</hi> was made. The Lord Chancellor <hi>Egerton</hi> ſaid it was a <hi>fooliſh</hi> Vow, and ordered an Attachment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. But what ill hap has touched our Author, as I know not, ſo I care not.</p>
            <p>There is another ſort of men (it ſeems) in the Inns of Court, with whom (I perceive) he has had more in timate acquaintance, for he deſcribes them knowingly, and they are <hi>the vain, imperfect, and half-witted part.</hi> Sir, It has been obſerved, that <hi>Venus</hi> had a Mole on her Cheek, <hi>Hellen</hi> a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:94173:62"/>Scar on her Chin, <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> a Wart, <hi>Lycurgus</hi> a Wen, and the Moon her Spots, and its proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that Societies made up of thouſands, may have among them ſome extravagants: and what then? Then it follows, as he ſays, there is a third ſort of men there <hi>of great abilities and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues;</hi> and to theſe he has nothing to ſay; but this I muſt ſay, it was his unhappineſs that his <hi>long experience,</hi> found them not out to converſe with; 'tis like they are part of the number of thoſe mentioned in his Preface, who are ſo <hi>retired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, Sir, For a little Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Is it ſo, that there are three ſorts of men in the Inns of Court, one too grave and moroſe, the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:94173:63"/>other too light and lewd, the third of <hi>Abilities and Vertues;</hi> then for Inſtruction, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to grave Adviſer) go not to <hi>London,</hi> but ſtay in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and learn of old Mother <hi>Huggins,</hi> to lay Eggs under her Sow to hatch Collops and Eggs, which will come to paſs at the ſame time, when a meer Booriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>life makes any one a <hi>Hero</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now, Sir, to the laſt ſort of vile People, that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Town ſuffers to reſide within her Walls: and though he tells you, <hi>that he is ſure you will not ſpend your time with them,</hi> yet he is reſolved <hi>Hit miſs,</hi> or <hi>Happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go-luck,</hi> (according to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Teutonick) to have a blow at their Jack: and theſe are a ſort
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:94173:63"/>of inconſiderable Muſhrooms, <hi>Groveling in Mechanicks, and pinioning the minds of men with mean Arts.</hi> What a Peſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od does this man mean? he ſtill miſtakes Terms and ſo underſtands not Arts. He took, ſure, <hi>Mechanick</hi> to be derived from the Town <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi> which he met with in <hi>Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Hiſtory,</hi> and thence conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that all Arts called <hi>echanick,</hi> were Infidel Arts, and brought hither by <hi>Turks,</hi> and ſo had an aſſurance, that you <hi>would not keep Company</hi> with ſuch <hi>Artiſts.</hi> What elſe he ſhould mean, is hard to conjecture; his <hi>medly</hi> deſcription putting us to a loſs in diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this dangerous <hi>Tribe,</hi> this Sect of <hi>New Philoſophers,</hi> for here is no <hi>New Philoſophy</hi> in Town.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:94173:64"/>Yet (methinks) I ſhould gueſs by his gaping what he means, may be the Epithet <hi>Mechanick,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſed (properly enough) to meaneſt Handicrafts, he thinks all Arts and Artiſts <hi>mean</hi> to which it's applied: but there is his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake and ignorance, however ſome Coffee-houſe-Wags, and <hi>Sonnet-Mongers</hi> (who (he ſays) have viſited him in the Country) may have fooliſhly in their rode of idle <hi>Droll</hi> thrown the notion into his Nodle; with ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due reflections.</p>
            <p>For there are, Sir, in this Town <hi>Mechanick Philoſophers</hi> in a Body compounded of the <hi>Royal Blood,</hi> the Nobility in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Prime</hi> of all the Learned men in <hi>England,</hi> and ſome Foreigners;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:94173:64"/>which Body has for its Head no leſs than that which wears an <hi>imperial</hi> Crown. Theſe are, Sir, the new Mecanick <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> whom your <hi>Remarker</hi> celebrates with the encomiums of <hi>groveling in Mechanicks, and pinioning mens minds with mean Arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Sir, out of reſpect to you, Ile tell you what <hi>Mechanick</hi> ſignifies; it comes from the Greek word which ſignifies Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice or Invention; and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanical</hi> Arts are now taken to be ſuch Arts in which the labour and uſe of the hand is required and are called ſuch in contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Arts barely Speculative, and Notional, and under that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, are contained, <hi>edicine, Military Diſcipline, Agriculture,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:94173:65"/>Cloathing, Navigation, Archite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,</hi> and many others, together (if you pleaſe) Hunting; in which laſt there is more Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy then all your Country and Adviſer too, underſtand.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>mean Arts,</hi> Sir, poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable <hi>London</hi> Philoſophers are glad to buſie themſelves withal, while <hi>Hugh Clodpate</hi> and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows (in the Country) can (as he ſays in the Play) content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with good Ale, Beef, Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, which are their own <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures,</hi> and with <hi>ſleeping quietly, dreaming gloriouſly,</hi> and ſporting on <hi>Natures beautiful Foot-cloaths,</hi> become <hi>Hero's</hi> of the Country ſtamp, and (by the help of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marker</hi>) <hi>rival</hi> the new <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> who have ſtored the World
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:94173:65"/>with ſuch a Body of Natural pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Philoſophy, and made it ſo ſubſervient to the Publike Good, that neither the <hi>Imperious Stagarite,</hi> (as he calls him) nor <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> among the Ancients, nor <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and the reſt of the Chymiſts of former Times, are very conſiderable, as was ſaid to be the hopes of the Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> had he lived, and is now the effects of the generous and noble Enterprizes of thoſe admirable perſons known by the illuſtrious Appellation of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi> And now again judge you, Sir, how <hi>ſure</hi> this Confident may be that <hi>you will not keep company with theſe perſons,</hi> there being ſcarce one ſingle perſon among them, whoſe company is not acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:94173:66"/>to the greateſt <hi>Hero's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On he goes, Sir, and meeting with the <hi>Merchant</hi> at half turn, gives him a fillip on the finger, and tells him he is one <hi>whoſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is Profit and Intereſt, without any deſign upon the improvement of Arms, Letters, or Converſation,</hi> nor worthy your Company, Sir, and ſo farewell him. In good time, the man ſeems to come to his Wits, and is now for <hi>Arms, Letters,</hi> and <hi>Converſation,</hi> which the Merchant, (by which, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he means all Traders) he ſays, is not for. Even as much (ſay I) as the meer Country Sir <hi>Simon,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Buff coat,</hi> Leading-Staff, the A, B, C, and Tub of Ale be <hi>Arms, Letters,</hi> and Converſation. And, Sir, as ſlight
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:94173:66"/>as he makes of <hi>Merchandize,</hi> all Ages have ſhewn men of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce</hi> as like <hi>Hero's</hi> as ever he ſaw, who have been Governors of Towns of War, and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of State: and though there is reported an Age (long ſince) to have been, in which it was accounted diſparagement to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with a Merchants Daughter; if that were true, it's now other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and Country <hi>Hero's</hi> find by Experience, that if <hi>Tradeſmens</hi> daughters become not Miſtreſſes, the <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> themſelves become Maſters of many great Mannors in ſpight of Country <hi>Hero-ſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Citizens</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> themſelves in general, what by reaſon of the aforeſaid occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Giving, and Lending
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:94173:67"/>moneys, and Daughters and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termarriages: the converſe and acquaintance thereby gained with perſons of higheſt Rank, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the help of inherent qualities derived from their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, being moſtly the Sons of Gentlemen, and the general im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the Knowledge and Manners of this Town. They are (at this day) become men of ſuch outward <hi>Parade,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward accompliſhments, that the better ſort of them are received by the beſt Gentry, and an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>London</hi> Mechanick out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does Juſtice <hi>Clodpate</hi> and his 2000 <hi>l. per annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, farewel Merchant, on goes <hi>Tarlton,</hi> and having danced two or three Jiggs with his <hi>Jews-trump</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:94173:67"/>and <hi>Tongs</hi> to make <hi>you</hi> merry; he falls <hi>himſelf</hi> into <hi>O ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamantis.</hi> Oh, ſweet Sir, what will your <hi>Mother</hi> ſay, if you miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry? <hi>She has ſet you in the Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Hero's,</hi> but ſhe <hi>muſt</hi> now ſee you <hi>growing dim and ſullied in the Circle of ſo bright a Race.</hi> What, <hi>Muſt</hi> again! Pray, Sir, for my ſatisfaction, if not for your own, when you ſee this man of <hi>Art</hi> next, ask him, ſuppoſing ſuch lewd People to be in <hi>London,</hi> (as it is to be feared there are too many there, and in the Country too) why <hi>muſt you</hi> be a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate? what damned Fate hangs over your head, that (of all men living) you <hi>muſt</hi> not come to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don?</hi> and if you do, <hi>you</hi> that are ſet by your Mother in the <hi>cluſter
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:94173:68"/>of Hero's,</hi> will by the <hi>Lawyers, New Philoſophers,</hi> and Poets, be ſet in the cluſter of Hell-hounds? ay, and you will dote ſo much on the <hi>Town,</hi> as you <hi>will be a ſtranger in your Country;</hi> ay, and (like Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) you <hi>muſt</hi> be a ſtranger in <hi>your</hi> Country. How, is Juſtice a ſtranger in <hi>your</hi> Country? I am ſorry to hear of ſo barbarous a <hi>Country;</hi> and believe it, I think it high time for you to <hi>remove,</hi> you are like to have pretious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, where's no Juſtice, and brave Country <hi>Hero's</hi> too, and good Juſticers: I fear your Man of Wrangle has railed the <hi>Lawyers</hi> out of your Country, and Juſtice with them; the Statute baniſhing the two <hi>Spencers,</hi> Father and Son, has this Article againſt them, that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:94173:68"/>they made Juſtices who were not converſant in the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land; they having in ſtead thereof, put <hi>ignorant</hi> men into thoſe Offices, whom they could eaſily <hi>impoſe</hi> upon, and warp to unjuſt attempts. Sir, if this be the Caſe of your Country, and the Cauſe that <hi>Juſtice is a ſtranger there,</hi> I think you <hi>muſt</hi> go to <hi>London,</hi> either to become a Lawyer, to converſe and acquaint with thoſe moroſe men of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> or to procure one or more to go inhabit <hi>your Country,</hi> that <hi>Juſtice</hi> may be no longer a <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> there; elſe (methinks) you hazard your ſelf among a Herd of <hi>Tories.</hi> This is (pardon me Sir) if the <hi>Remarker</hi> ſays true; and who knows, but he ſometimes
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:94173:69"/>do ſo? I verily believe him, when he ſays, <hi>Sir, We that have hither to been honoured with your Frindſhip, ſhall not know after what manner to receive you, when you return from the Town; we know you will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently deſpiſe not only our capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but our courage, whilest we can neither talk nor act at your admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rate: nor, I believe, will you ever be able to inſpire us with your gallantry of mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Whether this man be skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in <hi>Figures</hi> as well as <hi>Letters,</hi> and ſo how he intended theſe words, I know not, for men to whom <hi>Juſtice is a ſtranger,</hi> may ſay one thing and mean another. But (in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi>) after you have with ſobriety and induſtry imbibed the harmleſs and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:94173:69"/>improvements of the Town, and made your ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didate for a true <hi>Hero-ſhip,</hi> the Ignorantees and <hi>Clodpates</hi> of the Country will <hi>not know how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you</hi> at your return, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, you may look with a <hi>despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> Brow, or the <hi>capacities</hi> and <hi>courage</hi> of deſpicable Wretches, who live <hi>ſtrangers to Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>cannot talk nor act at your admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rate.</hi> And (which I believe will trouble you) <hi>you will not be able to inſpire them with your gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry of mind,</hi> they being ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to a <hi>ſleeping, dreaming</hi> life, deſtitute of the improvements you will be then Maſter of.</p>
            <p>And ſince, Sir, this Country Philoſopher has concluded ſo luckily for Truth; ſome few
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:94173:70"/>lines of his <hi>own,</hi> having anſwered all his Book; ſince (after ſome few Traverſes on the Stage with three or four Papers of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Experience</hi> in his hand) he has <hi>bequeathed</hi> them to you as the laſt Legacie of <hi>a dying Remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and ſo taken his leave of <hi>you.</hi> I ſhall only ſay to him, that as to ſome of his Letter; had it been well appointed to proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, it is not without its weight, and I wiſh it might obtain good ends; but, as to what is pointed towards you, with the many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable <hi>muſts,</hi> I take it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſignificant and idle, and ſhall tell him one ſtory more, and take leave of him.</p>
            <p>A <hi>French</hi> Mill-Wright, who was excellent, in his own conceit,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:94173:70"/>becauſe he could make a Mill well, thought he could make an Engine of Wheels that ſhould grind <hi>all</hi> ſorts of Corn, and with Edge-tools to turn Spits, and give the hour of the Day as a Clock: but having ſpent his brains and his pains about it, he was (at laſt) ſain to content himſelf with a Nut-cracker of it, and glad he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped ſo too.</p>
            <p>Now, Sir, as to you, after a hearty deſire tendred, to ſee a man of your <hi>growing</hi> hopeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Qualifications, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to be (by the help of due advantages and proper methods) improved into an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hero; and to ſee you at <hi>London</hi> for that end,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:94173:71"/>and with that reſolution; and with aſſurance of unfeigned pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to <hi>ſerve</hi> you in that deſign, I take leave, and remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sir, <hi>Your moſt affectionate humble Servant.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94173:71"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
